Guide to the Maxwell Harway papers, 1934-2007
George Mason University. Libraries. Special Collections Research Center
Maxwell Harway papers
1934-2007
C0120
George Mason University. Libraries. Special Collections Research Center
1.5 linear feet (2 boxes)
This collection contains materials pertaining to the long and varied career of Maxwell Harway, an economist with the United States Department of State and Department of Labor and a historian and critic of current affairs. Materials include reports and memoranda, newsclippings, business cards, and magazine articles.
Harway, Maxwell
Box 2
Box 1
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Collection donated by Max Harway in 2007.
Biographical Information
Maxwell Harway has had a long and varied career, which includes years working for the U.S. State Department, as an economist with the Department of Labor, and ultimately, as an adjunct history professor at George Mason University. Born in 1913, Harway grew up as a second-generation American son of White Russian immigrants on Manhattan's Lower East Side. He graduated from the prestigious Townsend Harris Hall high school in 1930. Among his classmates were Jonas Salk, inventor of the polio vaccine, actor Cornel Wilde, and author Herman Wouk.
After graduating from the City College of New York, Harway worked for the Works Progress Administration while presiding over a chapter of the American Federation of Teachers. In Washington in 1941, he became a chief economist for the federal Office of Price Administration, overseeing the rationing of sugar, coffee and other foodstuffs. He later spent 3 1/2 years in the U.S. Army Air Force, joined the State Department, and helped repair Europe's railroad and canal barge network under the Marshall Plan. In 1952 Harway received a master's degree in international relations from Georgetown University.
While applying for a faculty position at the University of Maryland in the 1950s, Harway encountered job discrimination as a Jew. He recalls the department head complementing his credentials but turning him down with the explanation, "I'm so sorry, we already have one Hebrew on the faculty."
Harway then entered a private minerals import-export business while living in Casablanca. In 1963, President Lyndon Johnson called on him to be a consultant in his War on Poverty, at a salary of $1 a year. A second State Department tour took Harway to Vietnam and Cambodia from 1965 to 1978, after which he moved to Warrenton. In recognition of Harway's accomplishments, especially his part in rebuilding Europe's transportation network after World War II, Clark University awarded him an honorary doctor of laws degree in 1996.
Harway later became president of the Fauquier Historical Society and turned to the county's history by writing articles, taking active roles in the Society, obtaining contributions so that Warrenton's Old Jail Museum could be open six days a week, and spearheading the celebration in August 2000 of the 175th anniversary of the Marquis de Lafayette's visit to Fauquier. In 2005, he began teaching modern U.S. and European history at George Mason University.
Scope and Content
This collection contains materials pertaining to the long and varied career of Max Harway, including reports and memoranda, newsclippings, business cards, and magazine articles. Items from earlier in his career include United States Department of State papers and reports from Harway's work as an economist with the Office of Price Administration's Division of Food Rationing during and after World War II. Items from later in his career include papers of the Fauquier Historical Society, of which Harway served as president, campaign ads to elect Harway to Warrenton Town Council, op-eds to various newspapers, and articles by Harway on the Middle East and China.
Arrangement
Organized by subject and date.
Related Material
Special Collections Research Center also holds other collections of personal papers on both national and Northern Virginia politics.
Index Terms
Persons:
Harway, Maxwell
Corporate Names:
Fauquier Historical Society.; United States. Dept. of State.
Geographical Names:
Fauquier County (Va.)--History.
Subjects:
International relations.; Local history.
Contents List
- List of works by Maxwell Harway, September, 1935 - February, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Scans of Harway's Newspaper articles on terrorism and the Middle East, December 3,1987 - September 23, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Article Clippings about China that include Harway, 1990's (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Notes on China Trip: by Maxwell Harway, May 17-18, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- "The End of Communism in China?" by Maxwell Harway, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- "Out of the Attic", April 20, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- "Talking Points on the Marshall Plan and Post Cold War Trade" Draft, by Maxwell Harway, January 20, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Remarks of Maxwell Harway at Clark University's convocation ceremony at Worcester, Massachusettes, May 19, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Maxwell Harway: Random Reflections of the Passing Century in Honor of Henry J. Leir, February 16, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- "To the Editor of the New York Times", July 3, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- A letter to the Editor of the Time's Dmocrat from Maxwell Harway, September 17, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- "On the Town: A two-story building with a thousand stories", July 24, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- "The Fauqier Citizen", August 22, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Memorandums to Maxwell Harway, September 18, 1953 - June 23, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Memorandums from Maxwell Harway, Ocotober 17, 2002 - October 21, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- "It's Your Government" by: Maxwell Harway, 1990's (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Town Council letter from Maxwell Harway, 1990's (Box 1, Folder 17)
- "North Africa" presented by Maxwell Harway Ad, September 22, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- "Reflections on the Departing Century" Ad, February 16, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Harway Hearing Proceedings, October 7, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Living History: At 92, Max Harway's past exploits are fodder for George Mason class, December 8, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Maxwell Harway's Resume, 1950's (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Harway's Campaign Speech Notes, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Max Harway Warrenton Town Council Advertisements, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Pictures of wine cellar and Max Harway campaign advertisements, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Photograph copy of Max Harway, 2000's (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Harway's Candidate biography, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Committee to elect Max Harway thank you letter, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Commonwealth of Virginia Sample Ballot, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Business cards / Identification for Maxwell Harway, Undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Interview #2 with Max Harway Questions, 2000's (Box 1, Folder 31)
- The Fauquier Democrat Newspaper clipping copies, December 1, 1983 - July 26, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- The Washington Post: Newspaper clipping copies, January 18, 1998 - March 26, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- The Fauquier Citizen Newspaper clipping copies, April 27, 1990 - November 20, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Newspaper clippings copies, March 6, 1940 - December 22, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Fauquier County and Warrenton, Virginia Visitors Guide, 2000's (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Fauquier National Bank Issued Check, November 13, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Fauquier County Chamber of Commerce update, December, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Fauquier Country Chamber of Commerce update, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- The Saga of the Warrenton Town Hall, April 15, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Old Town Warrenton Ad, 1990's (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Advertisement for the Wine Cellar Exhibit, 1990's (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Napoleon's Restaurant Menu and Short History, 1990's (Box 2, Folder 12)
- A Walking Tour of Warrenton Virginia pamphlet, 1990's (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Old Town Addition, 1990's (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Residential Consequences of Proposed Annexation, 1998 - 1999 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Lafayette Exhibition Artificat List, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Fauquier News: "Town Says 'Oui, Oui!' To Marquis", 2000 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Fauquier Times-Democrat: "Lafayette back in the news" clipping, May 26, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- The Weekender page copy, July 13, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- The Idler: "Warrenton, Virginia Salutes the Marquis De Lafayetter", September 6, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Booklet for Salute to Lafayette exhibit, September 15-17, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Salute to Lafayette brochures, September 15-17, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- News and Notes, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- News and Notes, Vol. 22, No. 2, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Interium Report on a Program for Distilled Spirits, 1934 - 1941 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Interium Report on a Price Program for the Wine Industry, 1934 - 1942 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- "Problems Inherent in the Development of a Points Rationing System", July 20, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Plans School, February 17 - March 3, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Inter-Governmental Transportation Coordinating Committee Notes and Report, September 26 - November 7, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Transportation Requirements for Lumber, December 13, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 30)
- U.S. Department of State: Documents and State Papers, Vol. 1, No. 8-9, November - December, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 31)
- The Department of State Bulletin: Vol. XXI, No. 522, July 4, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 32)
- The American Foreign Service Journal, Vol. 27, No. 1, January, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 33)
- Business Week: Traders brainchild a bonanza, February 3, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 34)
- Muslim Woman in the Middle East: Faces of Reality brochure, Nay 16, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 35)
- Constitution of the U.S: First Amendment (Establishment Clause), May 1, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 36)
- RRCSB-AAA Fiscal 2004 Program plan and meeting notice, June 19, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 37)
- Headquarters, North African Division, Air Transport Command (1250th AAF Base Unit) Plans Conference, December 14, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 38)
- North African Division Graduation Banquet Pamphlet, June 29, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 39)
- Letter about Harway from the North African Division Headquarters, November 28, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 40)
- "The Rocket Run" North African Division Booklet copy, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 41)
- Letter to Mr. Lipton from Sargeant Shriver and White House, March 31, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 42)
- A History of the 20th Century Vol. 3, 1952 - 1999 (Box 2, Folder 43)
- Chamber of Commerce Membership Applications, 1990's (Box 2, Folder 44)
- Danube Conference [CD-R], Undated (Box 2, Folder 45)
- Maxwell Harway Collection Photographs [CD-R], Undated (Box 2, Folder 46)